Guide to the Ellery Queen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ellery Queen papers
1929-1972
1946-1971
YCAL MSS 335
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.7
(2 boxes)
The Ellery Queen Papers document the mystery writing career of Frederic Dannay and Manfred B. Lee, writing as "Ellery Queen." The collection includes correspondence, fan mail, telegrams, advertisements, proposals for ventures, photographs, and ephemera relating to Ellery Queen. The collection does not include drafts of manuscripts, but includes American Weekly newspaper articles, likely written by Lee, with clippings describing authentic murder cases, and fan mail documenting their 1948 radio play "A Question of Color." Some of Manfred B. Lee's personal papers such as correspondence and photographs are also included.
Queen, Ellery
Dannay, Frederic, 1905-1982
Lee, Manfred B. (Manfred Bennington), 1905-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Manfred B. Lee, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ellery Queen
Ellery Queen is a pseudonym for the writing team of Frederic Dannay (1905-1982) and Manfred B. Lee (1905-1971). Dannay and Lee were cousins who entered a writing contest co-sponsored by McClure's Magazine and Lippincott's publishing house, and formed the joint venture of Ellery Queen. Although they did not win the contest, the cousins were rewarded with a book publication deal. Between 1928 and 1971, "Ellery Queen" wrote radio shows, a monthly magazine, a weekly newspaper series, novels, and television series all centered around the investigator "Ellery Queen." In the beginning of their writing career, Dannay and Lee kept their identities secret, but revealed their authorship in 1936. Although their work tended to be a "whodunit" type of story, the authors did address current issues or problems. Their most controversial work was a radio show called "A Question of Color", which debuted on February 12, 1948, and confronted the issue of racism in America. Dannay and Lee were also the co-writers of the Barnaby Ross mystery novels.
Scope and Contents
The Ellery Queen Papers document the mystery writing career of Ellery Queen, a pseudonym for Frederic Dannay and Manfred B. Lee. The collection includes correspondence, fan mail, telegrams, advertisements, proposals for ventures, photographs, and ephemera relating to Ellery Queen. The collection does not include drafts of manuscripts, but includes American Weekly newspaper articles, likely written by Lee, with clippings describing authentic murder cases. Some of Manfred B. Lee's personal papers such as letters, photographs, and cards are also included in the collection. The collection dates from 1929 to 1972, with the bulk of the material falling between 1946 and 1971.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1929-1971. II. Writings, 1931-1961. III. Other Papers, 1939-1972.
Detective and mystery stories, American -- 20th Century; True crime stories -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographic prints; Dannay, Frederic, 1905-1982; Lee, Manfred B. (Manfred Bennington), 1905-1971; Queen, Ellery; Mystery Writers of America -- Pictorial works; Baker Street Irregulars (Organization: U.S.) -- Pictorial works
- Correspondence, 1929-1971; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Manfred B. Lee Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence consists of professional correspondence related to Ellery Queen and some personal correspondence of Manfred B. Lee. Much of the correspondence consists of outgoing carbon-copied letters.
  The first subseries consists of general correspondence documenting the work of Ellery Queen. Correspondence with Jan Broberg includes a substantive response from "Ellery Queen" to interview questions. General correspondence also includes a folder of fan mail which documents the strong stance that Ellery Queen took against racism with the 1948 radio program "A Question of Color." Insight into Manfred B. Lee's personal opinion about this can be gained in a response letter. Also of interest are Lee's responses to fans in which he gives suggestions about how to start writing a mystery novel.
  The second subseries consists of Manfred B. Lee's personal correspondence. A 1947 outgoing letter to Bennett Cerf of Random House, written as a response to an article in SRL, details Lee's feelings towards political and social problems in the Bahamas at the time. Other substantive outgoing correspondence includes a 1961 letter to First Lady Jacqueline Kennedy regarding motherhood, with a response from her social secretary.
  - General correspondence
    General correspondence is organized alphabetically, with folders for "A Question of Color" fan mail and telegrams filed at the end.
    - Allen, Fred, 1955 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Borge, Victor, 1959 March 07 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Broberg, Jan, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      General note
      Includes a Swedish review of an Ellery Queen book
    - Buchanan, John D., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cheran, Mary, 1969 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1969 October 03 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company, 1952 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mann, Jacob, 1960 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Munn, James Buell, 1950 September (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - New American Library, Inc., 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes proof of Face to Face dust jacket
    - Playboy Enterprises, 1971 February 08 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Wallace, Mike, 1958 May 09 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes interview with Ellery Queen
    - Other correspondents A-Z, 1950-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "A Question of Color" fan mail, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Telegrams, 1929-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Manfred Lee correspondence, 1947-1969
    - Cerf, Bennett, 1947 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Outgoing letter only
    - Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1961 November (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Outgoing letter with response from Letitia Baldrige.
    - General correspondence A-Z, 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cards, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Writings, 1931-1961; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of murder victim.
  Series II consists of mystery stories published in American Weekly based upon authentic murder cases. American Weekly articles are often annotated, most likely by Lee, and most are accompanied by clippings documenting the original crimes. The majority of files were labeled with the name of the victim (V) and killer (K), and the original organization has been maintained.
  - K. Green, Major, 1937-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - K. Thompson, Thomas A., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - K. Fraden, Harlow, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - K. Gardner, Ray D. Dempsey, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - K. Snook, James H., Dr., 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - K. Bannister, May, 1936-1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - K. Schoplin, John, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - K. Mascari, Joseph, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - K. Seiler, Peter, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - K. Selz, Jerry, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - K. Saisi, Mary, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - K. Small, Frederick, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - K. Stott, Sam, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Post Office Detectives, 1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - K. Crawford, Jim, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - K. Kirby, Harry A. (James J. Crawford), 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - K. Smith, Winford, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - D'Autremont Brothers, 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - PA. Turnpike Murders, 1944-1955 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1958 (Box 2, Folder 40-42)
- Other Papers, 1939-1972; Series III
  Arranged by format.
  Series III consists of photographs, awards, and other material documenting the career of Ellery Queen. The photographs include an individual portrait of Frederic Dannay, a portrait of both Ellery Queen writers, the 1951 Mystery Writers of America, the 1946 Sherlock Holmes literary society called the Baker Street Irregulars, and photos of Lee at home with his family. The photographs of his family were taken for the Sunday Republican Magazine, and are undated.
  Materials documenting the Ellery Queen radio shows include a copy of a CBS advertisement and a listing of the dates and titles of the broadcasted shows, as well as casting cards. Ephemera includes the Ellery Queen letterhead, business card, envelope, and the Library of Congress catalog cards for Ellery Queen's Challenge to the Reader: an anthology. Materials documenting the Ellery Queen contest consist of a press release by NBC.
  - Awards, 1963-1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Biographies of Manfred B. Lee, undated, after 1971 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ephemera, 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Radio shows, 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Portrait of Frederic Dannay, photographs of Lee at home with his family
  - Photographs, 1946-1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Photographs of Ellery Queen, the Mystery Writers of America, and the Baker Street Irregulars
  - Press release, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 50)